American Philosophical Society Archives 1743-1984 APS.Archives
American Philosophical Society
- Library, 1798-1977; VII; 48.75 ln. ft.
  - Collections, 1798-1954; VII.2; 59.0 vols., 24.5 ln. ft.
    - Collections not acquired, 1972-; VII.2.i; 0.5 ln. ft.
    - Serial Records, 1896-1912; VII.2.j; 4.0 vols.
    - Exchange Records, 1936; VII.2.k; 1.0 vol.
  - Library. General correspondence and records, 1942-; VII.3; ca. 44 ln. ft.
    Files of selected professionals in the Library (e.g. Gertrude D. Hess, Carolyn Milligan) who were involved in administrative duties relating to the operation of the Library, and who had contacts outside of the Library.
  - Library Committee, 1897-1967; VII.4; 2.0 vols. & 2 ln. ft.
    - Committee Minutes, 1897-1967; VII.4.a; 2.0 vols. & 1.5 ln. ft.
      There are both original manuscript minutes, and more recently typed copies of same.
    - Report of the Committee on the Library, 1944; VII.4.b; 0.5 ln. ft.
      Survey data on specific subject areas represented in the Library's collections (Agriculture; Archaeology, Ethnology and Philology; Chemistry; Egyptology; Engineering; Geology; Indian linguistics; Medicine; Physics; and Serials) brought together by various scholars on the Library Committee. It was used in implementing the collection policy enunciated by the Farrand Committee in 1941 (see: "Report of the Special Committee on the Future Policy of the Library," Year Book, 1941 pp. 275-281; and, "Report of the Committee on Library," Year Book, 1944 pp. 51-57).
  - Library Administration, VII.5
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Consult Manuscripts Dept. Staff
  - Conservation Department, VII.6
    - General correspondence, VII.6.a
    - Treatment reports, VII.6.b
    - Binding orders, VII.6.c
    - Interns and volunteers, VII.6.d
  - Manuscript Department, VII.7
    - Correspondence, VII.7.a
    - Reader registration forms, VII.7.b
    - Orders and permissions, VII.7.c
  - Printed Materials Department, VII.8
  - Building and facilities, VII.9
    - Correspondence of the Library building, 1954-1960; VII.9.a; 4.0 ln. ft.
      Concerns specifications, equipment, and servicing the new library building, opened 1959.
    - Building Committee, Minutes, 1954-1957; VII.9.b; 1.0 folder
      Concerns the construction of the new library.
  - Exhibits, VII.10
    - Library Hall Exhibit materials, 1971-; VII.10.a
    - History of the Library Exhibit, VII.10.b
    - Benjamin Franklin Hall Exhibit, VII.10.c
    - APS and Exploration Exhibit, VII.10.d
    - Loans to external exhibits (includes Legacies of Genius), VII.10.e
  - Conferences, VII.11
    - Scientific Reprints Conference, 1984; VII.11.a
  - Publications, VII.12
    - Mendel Newsletter, VII.12.a
    - Library Bulletin (revived), VII.12.b
  - Friends of the Library, VII.13
    - Newsletter, VII.13.a
    - Miscellaneous Publications and Ephemera, VII.13.b
  - Financial Records, VII.14
  - Miscellaneous Records, VII.15; 6.0 ln. ft.
    - Permissions to Publish, VII.15.a
    - Library Statistics, VII.15.b
    - History of Genetics Project Card File, VII.15.c
- Committees, 1793-1977; VIII; 27.25 ln. ft.
  Consists of 36 sub-groups which document the activities of various committees formed over the Society's history to handle specific topics ranging from finance and grants to the Franklin Bicentenary and the construction of Library Hall.
  - Committee Record, 1793-1869, 1908-1915; VIII.1; 4.0 vols.
    A record of committees, their members, duties, dates of report, and disposition. The second volume contains a record of members' attendance, 1804-1833; and one volume - "Committee special" - lists three committees on "the State of the manuscripts," "the Franklin Mss.," and the revision of the society's laws and regulations, 1840-1842.
  - Advisory Committee. Minutes, 1933-1936; VIII.2; 1.0 vol.
    The committee was appointed to consider nomination of members.
  - Committee on Revision of Laws. Minutes, 1933; VIII.3; 1.0 vol.
    With letters and papers on the question whether residents of the District of Columbia were qualified, under the terms of the Society's charter, to vote and hold office in the Society.
  - Historical and Literary Committee. Minutes, 1815-1820, 1840-1843; VIII.4; 3.0 vols.
    The record of a committee which, under the leadership of Peter S. Du Ponceau, collected a large quantity of historical documents and letters of the colonial and Revolutionary periods of American history, and of materials on Indian Languages. An index of names and principal topics has been prepared.
    Minutes, mostly in the hand of John Vaughan, of meetings of the Committee; also lists of manuscript donations and summaries of incoming letters. May 9, 1815 - December 30, 1818, 69 pages; February 13, 1817 - August 18, 1820, 45 pages; July 10, 1840 - November 3, 1843, 8 pages.
    Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
  - Historical and Literary Committee. Letter books, 1816-1826; VIII.5; 3.0 vols.; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Donor, Peter S. Du Ponceau, 1836.
    A copybook kept by Peter S. Du Ponceau containing copies of letters sent by the committee to owners of historical manuscripts and to scholars and others interested in the early history of America, soliciting their cooperation, asking for the gifts of documents, thanking them, and the like.
    Includes letters on ethnology, history, and linguistics, as well as notes of conversations. The volumes are complemented by the Archives of the Society, the Heckewelder-Du Ponceau correspondence, and the personal papers of Du Ponceau at this library.
  - Finance Committee. Minutes, 1826-1898; 1913-1941; VIII.6; 5.0 vols.
    Established January 20, 1826, the committee was directed "to take charge, in conjunction with the Treasurer, of the investment of the Society's monies; and to have the general superintendence and management of the funds."
  - Finance Committee, 1898-1934; VIII.7; 1.0 box, 1 vol. (22 pp.)
    - List of securities, 1898-1902; VIII.7.a; 1.0 vol. (22 pp.)
    - Accounts, ca. 1840-1934; VIII.7.b; 1.0 box
  - Committee on Grants. Minutes and correspondence, 1933-1937; VIII.8; 1.0 vol. & 1 box
    The minutes cover the period 1933-1935. Originally the Committee on the Use of Funds for the Advancement of Knowledge through Investigation; now the Committee on Research.
  - Committee on Research. Grant applications, 1933-; VIII.9; ca. 116 ln. ft.
    These records are for the successful applicants. There is background data, such as letters of reference, and in some instances correspondence with the grantee. In many cases there is additional information that does not appear in the Year Book, which includes yearly lists of grants and more detailed reports on results of the grants as such reports are submitted. The Year Book also gives yearly tabulations of amounts of g rants, as well as cumulative tabulations.
  - Committee on Hall. Minutes and reports, ca. 1890-1939; VIII.10; 2.0 vols. & 1 box
    The committee was responsible for the buildings of the Society. The minutes cover the period 1907-1915, 1922-1939.
  - Committee on Publications. Minutes, 1826-1939; VIII.11; 3.0 vols.
    The committee was established by resolution of April 21, 1826.
  - Committee on Publications. Papers and records, 1826-1936; VIII.12; 2.5 ln. ft.
    Principally correspondence about publications, printing, and related topics.
    Included are an account book relating to subscriptions to the Transactions and Proceedings, and there are reports of the Publication Committee, 1831-1936.
  - Committee on Publications. Charles B. Trego's account, 1852-1873; VIII.13; 1.0 vol.
    Financial record for the APS Transactions.
  - Committee on Publications. Papers for publication, 1897-1927; VIII.14; 1.0 vol.
    An office record of papers submitted to the Society, with dates of reading, approval for printing, return of galleys, etc.
  - Committee on Publications. Requests for Society publications, 1866-1877; VIII.15; 1.0 box
  - Committee on Publications. Exchanges, 1871-1879, 1884, 1898; VIII.16; 1.0 box
    Lists of institutions and journals with which the Society exchanged publications.
  - Committee on Publications. Mailing lists, 1817-1874, 1885-1912; VIII.17; 4.0 vols. ̦ 1 box
    Record of members, institutions and others receiving the APS Proceedings and Transactions.
  - Committee on Publications. Hays Calendar material, 1946; VIII.18; 1.0 box
    Correspondence with the office of the Executive Officer about gifts to institutional libraries of copies of I. Minis Hays' Calendar of the Papers of Benjamin Franklin.
  - Committee on Education and Participation in Science. Papers, 1938-1942; VIII.19; 14.5 ln. ft.
    For the committee's study of amateur scientists and their organizations, see W. Stephen Thomas, ed., The Layman Scientist in Philadelphia(Philadelphia, 1940), and issues of the APS Year Book.
  - Committee on Mechanical and Physical Science. Minutes, 1834; VIII.20; 1.0 vol. (4 pp.)
  - Committee on Historical Manuscripts. Minutes, 1897-1904; VIII.21; 1.0 vol.
    Authorized December 17, 1897, "to examine the historical manuscripts and early American imprints in the Library of the Society," the committee was responsible for the following publications by the Society or commercial publishers: George Weedon's Valley Forge Orderly Book (Dodd, Mead, 1902); Calendar of the Correspondence Relating to the American Revolution ... (The Society, 1900); "Calendar of the Papers of Richard H. Lee," APS Proceedings 38 (1899): 114; Reuben G. Thwaits, ed., Journals of Lewis and Clark (Dodd, Mead, 1904-1905): and Documents Relating to the Purchase & Exploration of Louisiana (Houghton Mifflin, 1904). The minutes relate principally to these publications.
  - Committee on Franklin Bicentenary. Papers and records, 1906; VIII.22; 5.5 ln. ft.
    Includes correspondence, invitations and acceptance, bills, minutes, plans for reception, etc. for the Society's celebration of Franklin's anniversary. For the record of the anniversary see, The Record of the Celebration of the Two Hundredth Anniversary of the Birth of Benjamin Franklin .. April the seventeenth to April the twentieth, A.D. Nineteen Hundred and Six (Philadelphia, 1906), and the profusely illustrated scrapbook on the celebration, compiled by G. Albert Lewis (1829-1915) and presented by him to the Society, 1906. The minutes of the committee are bound with those of the Committee on the Bicentenary of the Society (VIII, 24). The minutes are concerned with the program, proceedings, and expenses of the anniversary meetings, and with the preparation of Hay's Calendar of the Papers of Benjamin Franklin (5 vols., Philadelphia, 1905-1906).
  - Committee on South Pole Exploration. Papers, 1909-1910; VIII.23; 1.0 vol. (ca. 30 pp.)
    Minutes, correspondence, reports, and newspaper clippings of a committee appointed in response to the Society's resolution of April 22, 1909, that the Society "request the cooperation of the scientific and geographical societies in the Country to urge the Government of the United States that it send a vessel ... to thoroughly explore and survey the coast of Wilkes Land, and other parts of Antarctica." For a discussion of certain aspects of this committee see, Stephen Catlett, "Supporting and preserving polar history: The American Philosophical Society and its collections," Fram: The Journal of Polar Studies 1 (1984): 297-310.
  - Committee on the Arrangement of the Bicentenary of the Society. Minutes, 1923-1926; VIII.24; 1.0 vol.
    Records concerning the program marking the 200th anniversary of the APS (then believed to have been founded in the Junto of 1727). See "Record of the Celebration of the Two Hundredth Anniversary ... of the American Philosophical Society ... April 27 to April 30, 1928," published as APS Proceedings 66 (1927). The minutes of the Committee on the Franklin bicentenary (see VIII, 22) are bound in this volume.
  - Committee on the Arrangement of the Bicentenary of the Society. Engrossed congratulations, 1927; VIII.25; 1.0 box
    Formal felicitations from learned societies and their appointed delegates to the APS bicentenary.
  - Magellanic Premium. Prize questions, ca. 1820; VIII.26; 1.0 vol. (5 pp.)
    Questions - 35 in all - under consideration for the Magellanic Premium.
  - Magellanic Premium. Entries, 1884-1913; VIII.27; 1.0 box
    Notes, memoranda, and essays submitted to the committee.
  - Phillips Prize Essay Committee. Papers, 1888-1921; VIII.28; 2.5 ln. ft.
    Minutes, reports of the committee, and copies of essays submitted for this prize in jurisprudence.
  - Committee on Nominations of Officers. Minutes, 1914-1940; VIII.29; 34.0 pp.
  - Franklin Writings Project Committee. Minutes, 1953-1958; VIII.30; ca. 60 pp.
    Includes background and organizational material concerning the creation of the Benjamin Franklin Papers editorial project, which was sponsored by the APS and headquartered at Yale University Library.
  - Committee on Foundation of APS. Report, 1914; VIII.31; 32.0 pp.
    Printed.
  - Committee on Policy. Minutes, 1932-1933; VIII.32; 1.0 vol. (ca. 75 pp.)
    Records numerous discussions on topics laid before the Society, e.g., nature of the Penrose Fund, care of the buildings, symposia, etc.
  - Phillips Library Fund Committee. Records, 1959-1977; VIII.33; 5.0 ln. ft.
    Includes minutes of meetings, applications for grants, lists of those accepted and some not chosen. There are also miscellaneous bits of related data.
    This fund was initially endowed through the residuary estate of Henry Phillips Jr., for the purchase of books and manuscripts on archaeology and philology. In the 1940s the scope was widened to allow for the support of archaeological and anthropological field work of both pre and postdoctoral researchers, who deposit their research data or reports on their work, in the APS Library.
  - Committee on History of Theoretical Physics in the Twentieth Century. Minutes, 1960-1961; VIII.34; 8.0 pp.
    The joint committee of the APS and the American Physical Society undertook the collection of oral history and manuscript material on the history of quantum physics. The results were published in, Thomas S. Kuhn, et al., Sources for the History of Quantum Physics (APS, 1967).
  - Bicentennial Executive and Planning Committee. Minutes and planning reports, 1973-1976; VIII.35; ca. 100 pp.
  - Planning Committee for the 1976 Congress on Liberty. Minutes and planning reports, 1968-1976; VIII.36; 50.0 pp.
- Financial Records, 1866-1957; IX; 4.75 ln. ft.
  Documents the Society's efforts from the mid-nineteenth through early twentieth centuries to raise funds in order to construct a new building in Philadelphia.
  - Trustees of the Building Fund. Minutes and accounts, 1866-1900; IX.1; 1.0 vol. (ca. 114 pp.)
    Authorized by resolution of October 5, 1866, to raise and hold money to construct a fireproof building for the Society, the trustees in 1900 turned over to the Society's general fund the small amount they had collected.
  - Building and Endowment Fund. Papers, 1911-1957; IX.2; 1.5 ln. ft.
    There are minutes, correspondence, signed pledges, and newspaper clippings relating principally to the Society's plan to erect a hall on the Benjamin Franklin Parkway. Also included are plans, letters, etc., from Paul Cret's office. The committee was first called Committee on Site for a New Hall.
  - Building and Endowment Fund. Ledgers, 1928-1933; IX.3; 2.0 vols.
    Principally a record of receipts during a financial campaign. For the inception and plan of this campaign, see the Society's prospectus, When Aristotle Comes Again (Philadelphia, 1929). The campaign was abandoned, the Society did not move, and the subscriptions, with the donor's permission, were eventually used to erect the Library, 1959.
  - Building and Endowment Fund. Scrapbooks, 1929-1931; IX.4; 11.0 vols.
    Newspaper cuttings, supplied by a clipping bureau engaged in connections with the fund-raising campaign of 1929.
- Meetings, 1901-1980; X; 0.75 ln. ft.
  Contains records relating to the Society's annual meetings during the twentieth century.
  - Records, X.1
    - Committee on General Meetings. Minutes, 1901-1923; X.1; 2.0 vols. (ca. 260 pp.)
      This committee functioned much like a program committee.
    - Committee on Papers. Minutes, 1909-1920; X.2; 1.0 vol. (ca. 75 pp.)
      Virtually a program committee, its minutes record its efforts to secure papers and lectures for the regular meetings of the Society.
    - Annual Meetings. Records, 1914-; X.3; 0.2 ln. ft.
      Includes announcements, programs, etc.
    - Annual Meetings. Attendance books, 1937-; X.4; 3.0 vols.
      - Attendance books; Visitors, and Members, 1942-1969; 1986-, 1985-; X.4.a; 3.0 vols.
      - Attendance Records, 1937-1975; X.4.b; Card File
    - Reports of General Meetings. Reports, 1936-1945; X.5; 0.5 ln. ft.
      Stenographic reports of informal discussions and addresses at general meetings and executive sessions of the Society. One is the report of a joint meeting with the National Academy of Sciences on "Atomic Energy and Its Implications," 1945; another contains the texts for after-dinner addresses by James T. Shotwell on world peace, Agnes Repplier on science and research, and Dugald C. Jackson on Elihu Thomson, 1937. Also included is a register of guests at General Meetings.
    - APS-Royal Society of London Meetings. Records, 1979-1980; X.6; 0.5 ln. ft.
      Background correspondence, comments on papers, a recording of the session, etc., for the first-ever joint meeting, which was held in June, 1980.
    - APS-Roy Swedish Academy of Science Joint Meeting. Records, 1998; X.7; 0.5 ln. ft.
  - Meetings Videos, 2003-2012; X.2
- Miscellaneous, 1794-1963; XI; 6.0 ln. ft.
  This record group consists of items which document the activities of the Society, but do not readily fall into one of the other record groups, and includes such items as the Society's weekly broadcasts during World War II, a register of visitors, and architectural plans of the Society's halls.
  - Letters and documents relative to a petition to the Pennsylvania Legislature for an appropriation for a "Franklin House", 1911-1913; XI.1; 1.0 vol.
    Contains a circular letter to members, 1911; circular letter to the Legislature, 1913; and related correspondence on one of the Society's many efforts to move from Independence Square to a more advantageous address in Philadelphia.
  - Miscellaneous legal papers, 1794-1963; XI.2; 6.0 ln. ft.
    Deeds, title searches, agreements to sell or buy, mortgages concerning the Society's lot on State-House Square and the site of a proposed building on the Benjamin Franklin Parkway; leases of rooms in Philosophical Hall to the Athenaeum of Philadelphia, the Pennsylvania Horticultural Society, the University of Pennsylvania, Charles Willson Peale, Thomas Sully, the United States marshal, and others; papers concerning Nathan Dunn's Chinese Museum property, 1829-1842; papers on the will of François André Michaux; correspondence and papers on the Magellanic Premium, the purchase of Franklin's books and manuscripts from Franklin Bache, 1936, the restoration of Franklin's house, construction of the Library building; material about bequests and gifts of I. Minis Hays, E. R. Johnson, R. A. F. Penrose, Jr., J. E. Whitfield. There are also recent data concerning gifts and deposits of manuscript collections, tax appraisals of same, etc.
  - Philosophical questions, 1801-1805; XI.3; 1.0 vol. (5 pp.)
    Queries by Robert M. Patterson and James Woodhouse relating to physics.
  - Weekly Broadcasts, 1941-1943; XI.4; 0.5 ln. ft.
    The Society sponsored, in cooperation with the World Wide Broadcasting Foundation, a series of lectures, principally on internationalism in science, "to those countries overseas where there is still interest in the progress of science and learning." Included in this group of documents are transcripts of the broadcasts, as well as some background letters and related material. For published reports by the Society on these broadcasts see the Year Book 1942-1943. Speakers include: Charles G. Abbot, W. Lloyd Aycock, Frank Aydelotte, Francis Biddle, Edwin G. Conklin, Edward S. Corwin, Karl K. Darrow, Sir Angus Fletcher, George Gallup, Cecilia Payne Gasposchkin, Philip C. Jessup, Alfred C. Lane, L. Don Leet, William Draper Lewis, Kirtly F. Mather, Elmer D. Merrill, Spencer Miller, Jr., Robert A. Milikan, Robert C. Murphy, Harlow Shapley, Horace W. Stunkard, W. F. G. Swann, and T. Wayland Vaughan.
  - Correspondence on the 150th anniversary of the Society, 1893; XI.5; 0.5 ln. ft.
    Contains printed invitations, programs, letters of acceptance and congratulations from other societies and from individuals. For an account of the celebration, see APS Proceedings 32 (1893): 5.
  - Visitors at the centennial celebration, 1843; XI.6; 1.0 vol.
  - Register of visitors, 1870-1942; XI.7; 2.0 vols.
    Autograph signatures of prominent visitors to annual meetings, as well as some members' signatures. Groups of autographs include those, for instance, who attended the International Geographic Congress in Philadelphia in 1904. Among many prominent visitors for the event were Francis and George Darwin, William Gilpin (governor of Pennsylvania), and Oswald Veblen.
  - Architectural Plans and renderings, ca. 1948-1958; XI.8; 3.5 ln. ft.
    Documents both for the Library and Philosophical Hall. There are also extra-oversized drawings and plans.
- History, 1840-1945; XII; 0.25 ln. ft.
  Consists of four accounts on the early history of the Society.
  - An historical account of the origin and formation of the American Philosophical Society, 1840; XII.1; 1.0 vol (ca. 175 pp.); Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    On a careful examination of the records, the author concluded that the APS was founded in the Junto of 1727. This volume also contains a letter of Du Ponceau to a committee of the Society relative to publication of the papers, 1841; the report of the committee which considered this paper and one by J. Francis Fisher on the founding of the Society; a statement on the attendance of members of the meetings, 1758-1768; abstracts from the minutes of the Junto; and a chronology of the history of the Society. The author withdrew his essay for the purpose of revising it, 1841.
    Du Ponceau's essay, the related documents mentioned above, and additional evidence and arguments were published by the Society in 1914 as part of the report of a committee, appointed 1910, "to investigate and determine the date of the foundation of the Society." Upon their recommendation, the Society adopted 1727 as its founding date. In 1948, however, it accepted again the more historically defensible date of 1743.
  - An account of the American Philosophical Society, n.d.; XII.2; 1.0 vol (9 pp.) Copy.; Vaughan, John
    A brief history and description of the Society sent to Baron Reonne, Prussian minister to the United States, 1841, in response to a query form the Prussian minister of public instruction.
  - The Rise of the American Philosophical Society, 1766-1787, 1949; XII.3; 1.0 vol Typed, Carbon; Hindle, Brooke
    Doctoral dissertation, University of Pennsylvania, 1949. Some of the material and conclusions of this authoritative study were used in the author's full account of The Pursuit of Science in Revolutionary America, 1735-1789 (Chapel Hill, 1956).
  - Miscellaneous articles. Historical Sketches., ca. 1940-1945; XII.4; 1.0 folder (ca. 40 pp.)
    There are brief sketches of the Society, prepared for various publications.
- Wistar Association, 1818-1968; XIII; 4.5 ln. ft.